<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Industrial Organization</title>
    <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Industrial Organization</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>1.1. Introduction and Overview</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.1-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.1-class/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Overview Slides Links   Overview An introduction to the course.
Slides   Lecture Slides  Links These are the articles mentioned in the slides:
On the California Law re: Employees vs. Contractors:
 Reason (Dec 17, 2019), “California Freelancers Suffer From Totally Predictable ‘Unintended Consequences’ of Gig Worker Protection Bill” SBNation (Dec 16, 2019), “California’s terrible AB5 came for me today, and I’m devastated” Washington Post (Dec 19, 2019), “How a law aimed at Uber and Lyft is hurting freelance writers” Washington Post (Sept 17, 2019), “A California bill has nationwide ramifications for the gig economy” Hollywood Reporter (Oct 17, 2019), “‘Everybody Is Freaking Out’: Freelance Writers Scramble to Make Sense of New California Law” New York Times (Dec 31, 2019), “California Wanted to Protect Uber Drivers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.2. Technology and Cost</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.2-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.2-class/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Overview Moblab Slides   Overview We begin our review/extension of basic production concepts from microeconomics. Today we focus primarily on production functions and costs. These will be relevant regardless of what kind of market structure we are looking at.
Moblab Please register an account at Moblab.com and join our class section with the code below:
We may play our first “game” this week or next to understand perfect competition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.2. Technology and Cost - Readings</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/1.2-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/1.2-reading/</guid>
      <description>Required Readings:  NONE  Recommended Readings: This is a part of our review of major production concepts from Microeconomics. You should consider looking at the following textbooks if you are rusty or want to know more about these concepts:
  Ch. 2: pp.29-40 in Dennis W Carlton and Jeffrey M PerloffModern Industrial Organization, 4th ed. (USA: Pearson, 2005).
  Ch. 2.1-2.2, 3.1 in Jeffrey Church and Roger WareIndustrial Organization: A Strategic Approach (New York: McGraw-Hill, 2000).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.3 Perfect Competition I: Short Run</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.3-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.3-class/</guid>
      <description> Contents  Overview Moblab Slides   Thursday, January 23, 2020
Overview We begin our review/extension of perfect competition by looking at how firms maximize profits in the short run.
Moblab Please register an account at Moblab.com and join our class section with the code below:
We may play our first “game” this week or next to understand perfect competition.
Slides   Lecture Slides  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.3. Perfect Competition I: Short Run - Readings</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/1.3-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/1.3-reading/</guid>
      <description>Required Readings:  NONE  Recommended Readings: This is a part of our review of major production concepts from Microeconomics. You should consider looking at the following textbooks if you are rusty or want to know more about these concepts:
  Ch. 3 in Dennis W Carlton and Jeffrey M PerloffModern Industrial Organization, 4th ed. (USA: Pearson, 2005).
  Ch. 2.1-2.2, 3.1 in Jeffrey Church and Roger WareIndustrial Organization: A Strategic Approach (New York: McGraw-Hill, 2000).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.4 Perfect Competition II: Ong Run</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.4-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.4-class/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Overview Moblab Slides   Tuesday, January 28, 2020, Thursday, January 30, 2020
Overview We continue our review/extension of perfect competition by looking at how to derive the equilibrium for the industryover the long run, where entry and exit are possible. We also discuss the role of economic rents.
Moblab Please register an account at Moblab.com and join our class section with the code below:
We may play our first “game” today or next class to understand perfect competition:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.4. Perfect Competition II: Long Run - Readings</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/1.4-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/1.4-reading/</guid>
      <description>Required Readings:  NONE  Recommended Readings: This is a part of our review of major production concepts from Microeconomics. You should consider looking at the following textbooks if you are rusty or want to know more about these concepts:
  Ch. 3 in Dennis W Carlton and Jeffrey M PerloffModern Industrial Organization, 4th ed. (USA: Pearson, 2005).
  Ch. 2.1-2.2, 3.1 in Jeffrey Church and Roger WareIndustrial Organization: A Strategic Approach (New York: McGraw-Hill, 2000).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.5 Monopoly I: Behavior</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.5-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.5-class/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Overview Slides Appendix Price Elasticity of Demand Refresher Derivation of the Lerner Index    Thursday, January 30, 2020 and Thursday, February 6, 2020
Overview We begin looking at monopoly by discussing how a monopolist (as compared to a price-taking firm) chooses both its output and its price to maximize profits.
Slides   Lecture Slides  Appendix Price Elasticity of Demand Refresher Price elasticity of demand measures how much (in %) quantity demanded changes in response to a (1%) change in price.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assignments</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/assignments/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/assignments/</guid>
      <description>Grade Calculator  Use this tool to calculate your final course grade and predict what grades you would need on remaining assignments to obtain a desired course grade.
Homeworks There will only be a handful o homework assignments this semester, mostly in the first third of the course (where we are reviewing and practicing models). These questions will help check your understanding and mastery of the material, and will be a combination of quantitative, graph, and short answer questions of examples.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reference</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/reference/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/reference/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Tips for Success   Look here over the course of the semester for resources, links, and tips on how to succeed in the course, how to write well, and other things of interest related to economic development.
Tips for Success Take notes. On paper. Really. Studies show that using pen and paper trump taking notes on a device. The main reason is because you cannot possibly write down everything I am saying by hand.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schedule</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/schedule/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/schedule/</guid>
      <description>This page contains all of the following resources for each class meeting:
  Readings include textbook chapters and occasional journal articles  Assignments are due by the beginning of class unless otherwise stated  Class materials contain extra explanations, math/statistical properties &amp;amp; proofs, and other helpful resourcesThese “online appendices” keep the slides nice and de-cluttered!
  Slides are “Xaringan” presentations in html that can be opened in any browserFile &amp;gt; Print &amp;gt; Save as PDF if you wish to download them</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Syllabus</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/syllabus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/syllabus/</guid>
      <description>Download as PDF Last Updated: January 20, 2020  Industrial Organization&amp;#8853;Instructor
Dr. Ryan Safner
 118 Rosenstock
safner@hood.edu
@ryansafner
 Office hours: MW 3:15–5:00PM
Course
 TuTh
 January 15–May 8, 2020
 2:00–3:15PM
 101 Rosenstock
 is one of the most common fields of applied microeconomics. It traditionally studies business firms and their relationship to the market–how they make economic decisions, how they are affected by government regulation, how they strategically interact with one another–and how these change in markets that are more or less competitive–monopoly, oligopoly, monopolistic competition, or perfect competition, often with a close connection to antitrust law.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>