<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Classes on Industrial Organization</title>
    <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Classes on Industrial Organization</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>1.1. Introduction and Overview</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.1-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.1-class/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Overview Slides Links   Overview An introduction to the course.
Slides   Lecture Slides  Links These are the articles mentioned in the slides:
On the California Law re: Employees vs. Contractors:
 Reason (Dec 17, 2019), “California Freelancers Suffer From Totally Predictable ‘Unintended Consequences’ of Gig Worker Protection Bill” SBNation (Dec 16, 2019), “California’s terrible AB5 came for me today, and I’m devastated” Washington Post (Dec 19, 2019), “How a law aimed at Uber and Lyft is hurting freelance writers” Washington Post (Sept 17, 2019), “A California bill has nationwide ramifications for the gig economy” Hollywood Reporter (Oct 17, 2019), “‘Everybody Is Freaking Out’: Freelance Writers Scramble to Make Sense of New California Law” New York Times (Dec 31, 2019), “California Wanted to Protect Uber Drivers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.2. Technology and Cost</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.2-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.2-class/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Overview Moblab Slides   Overview We begin our review/extension of basic production concepts from microeconomics. Today we focus primarily on production functions and costs. These will be relevant regardless of what kind of market structure we are looking at.
Moblab Please register an account at Moblab.com and join our class section with the code below:
We may play our first “game” this week or next to understand perfect competition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.3 Perfect Competition I: Short Run</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.3-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.3-class/</guid>
      <description> Contents  Overview Moblab Slides   Thursday, January 23, 2020
Overview We begin our review/extension of perfect competition by looking at how firms maximize profits in the short run.
Moblab Please register an account at Moblab.com and join our class section with the code below:
We may play our first “game” this week or next to understand perfect competition.
Slides   Lecture Slides  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.4 Perfect Competition II: Long Run</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.4-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.4-class/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Overview Moblab Slides   Tuesday, January 28, 2020, Thursday, January 30, 2020
Overview We continue our review/extension of perfect competition by looking at how to derive the equilibrium for the industryover the long run, where entry and exit are possible. We also discuss the role of economic rents.
Moblab Please register an account at Moblab.com and join our class section with the code below:
We may play our first “game” today or next class to understand perfect competition:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.5 Monopoly I: Behavior</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.5-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.5-class/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Overview Slides Appendix Price Elasticity of Demand Refresher Derivation of the Lerner Index    Thursday, January 30, 2020 and Thursday, February 6, 2020
Overview We begin looking at monopoly by discussing how a monopolist (as compared to a price-taking firm) chooses both its output and its price to maximize profits.
Slides   Lecture Slides  Appendix Price Elasticity of Demand Refresher Price elasticity of demand measures how much (in %) quantity demanded changes in response to a (1%) change in price.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.6 Monopoly II: Consequences</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.6-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.6-class/</guid>
      <description> Contents  Overview Slides   Thursday, February 6, 2020 and Tuesday, February 11, 2020
Overview We continue looking at monopoly and see what are the economic consequences of monopoly.
Slides   Lecture Slides  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.6 Monopoly III: Pricing</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.7-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.7-class/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Overview Slides Readings and Discussion   Tuesday, February 11, 2020 and Thursday, February 13, 2020
Overview We finish our look at monopoly and market power with a look at how a firm with market power decides how to set multiple prices.
Slides   Lecture Slides  Readings and Discussion For next class, we will have our first discussion on monopoly, please see the relevant readings and questions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.8 Factor Markets</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.8-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/1.8-class/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Overview Slides Homework 1 due February 27   Thursday, February 20, 2020
Overview Today we cover a topic that often does not get covered in microeconomics courses, but is important nonetheless for our purposes: markets for factors of production (e.g. land, labor, capital, supplies, etc). We discuss what determines prices in these markets, and how they vary with monopoly power and monopsony power (a buyer with market power).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2.2 Cournot Competition</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/2.2-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/2.2-class/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Overview Slides Appendix Cournot Competition, Abstracted Cournot Theorem    Thursday, February 20, 2020
Overview Today we cover a topic that often does not get covered in microeconomics courses, but is important nonetheless for our purposes: markets for factors of production (e.g. land, labor, capital, supplies, etc). We discuss what determines prices in these markets, and how they vary with monopoly power and monopsony power (a buyer with market power).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2.4 Sequential Games</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/2.4-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/2.4-class/</guid>
      <description> Contents  Overview Class Livestream/Lecture Videos Slides Appendix   Tuesday, March 24, 2020
Quarantine Lecture 1
Overview Today we take a deeper dive into game theory, as some more advanced tools will help us think about firms and industries going forward.
Class Livestream/Lecture Videos  See the above video for a brief overview of Zoom.
  Zoom Live Class Meetings (starts Tuesday at 2:00)      Slides   Lecture Slides  Appendix  See some visualizations I made: Cournot: Symmetric Market Changes Cournot: Asymmetric Costs Cournot: With n Firms   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2.5 Contestability &amp; Entrepreneurship</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/2.5-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/2.5-class/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Overview Class Livestream/Lecture Videos Slides Assignments: Homework 2, Midterm Exam   Thursday, March 26, 2020
Quarantine Lecture 2
Overview Today we wrap up Unit 2 with a brief final application of game theory to contestable markets, and then a more literary-inspired discussion of the shortcomings of “perfect competition” as a realistic, policy-relevant model.
Class Livestream/Lecture Videos      Slides   Lecture Slides  Assignments: Homework 2, Midterm Exam Homework 2 is posted, and is due via email, on Sunday, April 5, by 11:59PM.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3.1 Why Are There Firms?</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/3.1-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/3.1-class/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Overview Readings Class Livestream/Lecture Videos Slides Assignments: Homework 2, Midterm Exam Midterm Course Grades   Tuesday, March 31, 2020
Quarantine Lecture 3
Overview Today we start looking at what is known in economics as “the theory of the firm.” We begin with asking the question, “if markets are so great, why are there firms?” We look at Adam Smith’s idea of the division of labor, and when specialization makes sense.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3.2 The Firm as Nexus of Contracts</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/3.2-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/3.2-class/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Overview Readings Class Livestream/Lecture Videos Slides Discussion Board Assignments: Homework 2, Midterm Exam   Thursday, April 2, 2020
Quarantine Lecture 4
Overview Today we continue looking at the “theory of the firm” launched by Coase (1937). We explore a famous interpretation (among other intepretations) of the firm as a “nexus of contracts” in the marketplace. This comes from a famous paper by Alchian and Demsetz (1972), which views the firm not as a command-and-control hierarchy, but another nexus of voluntary market transactions, where collaborating factors of production find it in their interest to hire a monitor to minimize shirking, and give the monitor residual claimancy over the output.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3.3 Asset Specificity Theory</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/3.3-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/3.3-class/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Overview Readings Class Livestream/Lecture Videos Slides Discussion Board Assignments: Midterm Exam Due 8 PM Saturday April 11   Thursday, April 2, 2020
Quarantine Lecture 4
Overview Readings See today’s readings which may help you understand the concepts, and which are the primary source of what I discuss today.
Class Livestream/Lecture Videos Slides   Lecture Slides  Discussion Board I have opened up a discussion board on BlackboardGo to this course on Blackboard, on the blue navigation bar on the left, see Discussion Board.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transition to Online Course For Spring 2020</title>
      <link>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/online-transition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ios20.classes.ryansafner.com/class/online-transition/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Overview Changes to Course Structure &amp;amp; Assignments Specific Changes for Current Assignments 1. Position Paper 2. Homeworks 3. Resuming Classes    Overview Welcome to online classes from quarantine!
None of us signed up for this. Some of you may be dealing hardships at home and at work, and may be juggling many problems right now. It may be awkward and difficult for you to learn at home, and for me to teach from home.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>